John Vassos Papers
John Vassos Papers
1928-1981
Vassos, John, 1898-1989
7.5 linear ft., incl. 232 oversize items
The collection consists of the artwork and professional papers of John Vassos. Arranged in four categories (Correspondence-Subject File, Artwork, Writings, and Memorabilia), the collection focuses on Vassos' creative efforts as an arts administrator (Silvermine Guild of Artists), an innovative illustrator (The Ballad of Reading Gaol, Phobia), and an industrial designer. The collection includes correspondence, designs, drawings, photographs, paintings, essays, books, memorabilia and printed material.
148718
Biographical History
Greek-American industrial designer, painter, illustrator, author, Vassos worked to establish industrial design as a profession with a strong academic foundation. A founding member of the American Designers Institute (ADI) and the Industrial Designers' Institute (IDI), Vassos played a major role in the 1965 merger of the Industrial Designers' Institute (IDI), the American Society of Industrial Designers (ASID), and the Industrial Design Education Association (IDEA) to form the Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning the years 1928-1981, the collection consists of the artwork and professional papers of the Greek-American artist, author, industrial designer, and illustrator John Vassos (1898-1985). Arranged in four categories (Correspondence-Subject File, Artwork, Writings, and Memorabilia),the collection focuses on Vassos' creative efforts as an arts administrator (Silvermine Guild of Artists), an innovative illustrator (Salome, The Ballad of Reading Gaol, The Harlot's House, Contempo, Ultimo, Gray's Elegy, Kubla Khan, Phobia, Humanities, ), and an industrial designer (accordians for Hohner; computers, an electron microscope, radios, and televisions for RCA; as well as corporate logos, shotguns, and turnstyles).
The collection also reflects Vassos' work in establishing Industrial Design as a profession with a strong academic foundation. Collection materials testify to Vassos' efforts to educate businessmen with the help of other designers and to speak with design students at Syracuse University, the University of Bridgeport, and the University of Cincinnati. A founding member of the American Designers Institute (ADI) and the Industrial Designers' Institute (IDI), Vassos played a major role in the 1965 merger of the Industrial Designers' Institute (IDI), the American Society of Industrial Designers (ASID), and the Industrial Design Education Association (IDEA) to form the Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA).
The Correspondence-Subject File contains correspondence and related material from clients, colleagues and friends, and organizations. Among Vassos' clients were Kuljian, Prudential Lines, Inc., and the Radio Corporation of America (RCA), and material includes correspondence, designs, publications, and memorabilia relating to these companies. Colleagues and friends whose correspondence is represented include Constantinos Doxiadis, Martin Kamin, Tucker Madawick, Joseph Parriott, Arthur Pulos, and Rex Rand. Organizational material, consisting of correspondence, publications, and memorabilia, relates to the Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA) and the Silvermine Guild of Artists. The Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA) materials pertain to the early organizational structure of the Society and also feature designs by Vassos.
Artwork includes designs (Bendix, "The Bible," M. Hohner, Inc., and Italian Lines Steamship Agency, Inc.) and drawings as well asoriginal and published illustrations. There are also photographs of some of Vassos' paintings and reproductions of some of his other work.
Books which Vassos wrote and illustrated as well as drafts and published versions of essays constitute Writings. Essays, many of which concern the contributions of industrial design to society, appeared in various design and corporate journals, regional magazines, and newspapers.
Memorabilia comprises calendars, financial and legal material, documents pertaining to Vassos' military career, and assorted printed material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Industrial Design; Art -- Illustrators; Chapman, David.; Doxiades, K. A. (Konstantinos Apostolou), 1913-1975.; Kamin, Martin.; Kaufmann, Edgar, 1910-; Madawick, Tucker P.; Miller, Leon Gordon.; Parriott, Joseph M.; Pulos, Arthur J.; Rand, Rex.; Spilman, Raymond, 1911-; Vassos, John, 1898-1985.; American Society of Industrial Designers.; Industrial Design Education Association.; Industrial Designers' Institute.; Industrial Designers Society of America.; RCA Corporation.; Silvermine Guild Center for the Arts.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Art deco -- United States.; Design, Industrial -- United States.; Greek American artists.; Illustrators -- United States.; Industrial designers -- United States.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Essays.; Illustrations.; Photographs.; Artists.; Illustrators.; Industrial designers.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical and Family material, 1938; 1963-1974,; undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Subject File
  - A, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Allcom Company, Inc., 1964; 1966 (Box 1)
  - American Designers Institute (ADI), See Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA)
  - American Society for Neo-Hellenic Studies, Inc., 1964; 1973 (Box 1)
  - American Society of Industrial Designers (ASID), See Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA)
  - The Argonaut, 1972; 1974 (Box 1)
  - Atlantis, 1972; undated (Box 1)
  - B, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Baer, Albert M., 1964-1974 (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, Faith, undated (Box 1)
  - Buttitta, Tony, 1968 (Box 1)
  - C, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Chapman, David, See Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA)
  - Cherepov, George, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Christian, John, undated (Box 1)
  - Columbia University, 1963-1974 (Box 1)
  - D, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Doxiadis, Constantinos A., 1965-1971 (Box 1)
  - E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., 1968-1975 (Box 1)
  - E-F, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Felix, Mary, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    See also American Society for Neo-Hellenic Studies, Inc.
  - Field trial clubs, 1949-1962; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Finch College Museum of Art, 1970 (Box 1)
  - French, Benjamin I., 1975-1977; See also Radio Corporation of America (RCA) (Box 1)
  - G, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Guilfoyle, Roger, 1971; undated (Box 1)
  - H-I, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Industrial Design Education Association (IDEA), See Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA) (Box 1)
  - Industrial Designers' Institute (IDI), See Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA) (Box 1)
  - Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA), 1941-1981; undated
    - Correspondence (General), 1948-1978; undated; 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Committees
      - Bicentennial of American Design (Box 1)
      - Education, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Grievance Inter-Society Licensing, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Nominating (Box 1)
      - Safety (Box 1)
    - Designs (Box 1)
    - Designs, oversize (Map-case 50)
    - Meetings
      - Board of Directors, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Design awards, See Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA): Meetings: National
      - National, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Regional (Box 2)
    - Membership directories, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Publications
      - News releases (various), 1965; undated (Box 2)
      - News releases about Vassos, ca. 1955; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Periodicals - ms drafts, production records, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Periodicals (various issues), 1941-1972; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Reports (Box 2)
    - Memorabilia
      - Printed material about IDSA (Box 2)
      - Clippings, 1965 (Box 2)
      - Promotional material (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Irwin, Donald, 1972; undated (Box 2)
    See also Norwalk, CT
  - J-K, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Kamin, Martin, 1967-1971; undated (Box 2)
  - Kaufmann, Edgar, See Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA)
  - Kiwanis Club, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Kuljian
    - Correspondence, 1968-1970; undated (Box 2)
    - Designs (Box 2)
      Projects, Standards
    - Promotional material, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - L, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Lilly, Elisabeth, 1966-1973; undated (Box 2)
  - Lord, Clifford Lee, 1965 (Box 2)
    See also Columbia University
  - M, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Madawick, Tucker P., 1968-1975 (Box 2)
    See also Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA) and Radio Corporation of America (RCA)
  - Miller, Leon Gordon, See Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA)
  - N, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - National Art Museum of Sport, 1962-1973; undated (Box 2)
  - New York University, 1950; 1952 (Box 2)
  - Norwalk, CT, 1968-1975; undated; 1 folder (Box 2)
  - O, 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Onassis, Aristotle Socrates, 1968 (Box 3)
  - P, 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Parriott, Joseph, 1965; 1971 (Box 3)
    See also Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA)
  - Parsons School of Design, 1964-1966 (Box 3)
  - Pavilions, 1954-1957; 1964,; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
    See also Radio Corporation of America (RCA): Designs and Artwork: Designs: Pavilions
  - Perry, Helen Swick, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1964-1965; 1971,; undated (Box 3)
  - Pratt Institute, 1954; 1971-1973,; undated (Box 3)
  - Prudential Lines, Inc., 1965-1974; undated
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Designs
      - Projects, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Projects, oversize (Map-case 50)
      - Standards (Box 3)
      - Promotional material (drafts) (Box 3)
      - Promotional material (Box 3)
      - Memorabilia (Box 3)
      - Clippings, 1967-1970 (Box 3)
  - Pulos, Arthur (Box 3)
    See also Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA) and Syracuse University
  - Q-R, 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Radio Corporation of America (RCA), 1934-1976; undated
    - Correspondence (General), 1945-1975; undated; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Committees - Advanced Design and Styling Center Advisory Board (Box 3)
    - Designs
      - The American Style (Box 3)
      - International sketches, 1947 (Box 3)
      - Magictron (Box 3)
      - Pavilions (Box 3)
      - Projects (miscellaneous), 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Projects, oversize, 2 folders (Map-case 50)
      - Standards, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Trademark (Box 3)
    - Publications
      - Annual reports, 1959-1974; 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Broadcast News, 1948; 1960-1961,; 1968,; 1969
        - Miscellaneous issues, 3 folders (Box 4)
        - News releases, 1960; 1972,; undated (Box 4)
        - Periodicals - miscellaneous issues (Box 4)
        - Promotional material, 4 folders (Box 4)
        - RCA Art Collection, undated (Box 4)
      - Reports
        - By Vassos (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Memorabilia
        - Clippings, 1952; 1968-1969,; 1976,; undated (Box 4)
        - Vassos tribute (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Rand, Rex, 1954-1973; undated (Box 4)
  - Risom, Jens, 1958; 1959 (Box 4)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A., 1970 (Box 4)
  - Russian Dollar Bondholders Committee of the U.S.A., 1964-1973; undated (Box 4)
  - S, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Silvermine Guild of Artists, 1950-1973; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Skouras, George, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Society of Industrial Designers (SID) (Box 4)
  - Spilman, Raymond (Box 4)
  - Stanford University, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Syracuse University, 1973-1974; undated (Box 4)
  - T, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Trade fairs, See Pavilions
  - U, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - United States Department of Commerce, See Pavilions
  - United States Foreign Service, See Pavilions
  - United States Information Agency (USIA), See Pavilions
  - University of Bridgeport, 1967-1973; undated (Box 4)
  - University of Cincinnati, 1974 (Box 4)
  - V, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Veterans of the Office of Strategic Services (O.S.S.), 1965-1973; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - W-Z, unidentified, 1 folder (Box 4)
- Artwork
  - Designs
    - Architectural drawings (miscellaneous) (Map-case 50)
    - Bendix (Box 4)
    - "The Bible" A-Z, 1928-1952; undated; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Chromespun House of Color (Map-case 50)
    - French, Narti, 1974; undated (Box 5)
    - M. Hohner, Inc., 1974; undated (Box 5)
    - M. Hohner, Inc., oversize items (Map-case 50)
    - Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA), See Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA): Designs
    - Italian Lines Steamship Agency, Inc., 1974 (Box 5)
    - Kuljian, See Kuljian: Designs
    - Pavilions (Map-case 50)
    - Prudential Lines, Inc., See Prudential Lines, Inc.: Designs
    - Radio Corporation of America (RCA), See Radio Corporation of America (RCA): Designs
    - Shotgun (Map-case 50)
    - Miscellaneous projects, 1948-1972; undated (Box 5)
  - Drawings, misc, 11 items (Box 5)
  - Illustrations (original)
    - "The Abduction of Helen of Troy", 1935; 1 item (Map-case 47)
    - The Courier, 1968; 1 item (Box 5)
    - Humanities, 1935; pp. 101 - Waste (numbers refer to page numbers in Contempo, Phobia and Other Graphic Interpretations, Dover Publications, 1976); 1 item (Map-case 47)
    - Kubla Khan, 1934; 8 items (Map-case 47)
      Arabic numerals refer to "stanzas" as numbered by Vassos, Roman numerals to "page number"
      1 - xxiii - In Xanadu...
      2 - xxvii - Where Alph...
      4 - xxxv - And Here Were Gardens...
      7 - xdvii - And From This Chasm...
      8 - di - Amid Whose Swift Half-intermitted Burst...
      10 - dix - And 'Mid This Tumult
      11 - dxiii - The Shadow Of The Dome Of Pleasure...
      13 - dxxi - And All Who Heard...
    - Phobia, #49-54, 1931 (Map-case 47)
      Numbers refer to page numbers in Contempo, Phobia and Other Graphic Interpretations, Dover Publications, 1976
      49 - Frontispiece
      50 - Nyctophobia
      51 - Astrophobia
      52 - Zoophobia
      53 - Potamophobia
      54 - Hylophobia
    - Phobia, #55-71, 1931 (Map-case 48)
      55 - Necrophobia
      56 - Acrophobia
      57 - Climacophobia
      58 - Batophobia
      59 - Dromophobia
      60 - Aichmophobia
      61 - Agrophobia
      62 - Claustrophobia
      63 - Monophobia
      64 - Topophobia
      65 - Kleptophobia
      66 - Mysophobia
      67 - Anthropophobia
      68 - Phagophobia
      69 - Syphilophobia
      70 - Hypnophobia
      71 - Pantophobia
    - Ship (Map-case 49)
    - Subway, "The First Subway Drawing in Charcoal", 1926 (Map-case 47)
  - Illustrations (published)
    - Coleridge, Samuel Taylor - Kubla Khan, 1933; 1934
    - The Courier no. 29, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Wilde, Oscar - The Ballad of Reading Gaol, 1928; 1930
    - Wilde, Oscar - The Harlot's House and Other Poems, 1929
  - Paintings (photographs) (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (reproductions) (Box 5)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Contempo, Phobia, and Other Graphic Interpretations, 1976
    - Phobia, 1931
  - Essays
    - "The Artist's Foreword", 1934 (Box 5)
      ms. draft - Kubla Khan
    - "As the Walls Come Tumbling Down" (Box 5)
      ms. draft
    - "Challenge and Opportunity", undated (Box 5)
    - "The Chromespun House of Color for the Young in Heart," John Vassos / Thomas H. Yardley, 1959 (Box 5)
    - "Controlled Light" - Interiors, Feb. 1948 (Box 5)
    - "Design for Selling" - Sales Executives Club Weekly News Bulletin, 24 May 1935 (Box 5)
    - "Designing in Depth - Reflections" - IDSA American Designer, Dec 1966 (Box 5)
    - "Designing Today's Living Room" - Upholstering, Jun 1946 (Box 5)
    - "Future Designers Tackle Gas Stations" - County, Oct 1967 (Box 5)
    - "Imagination is Not Enough" - County, Jan 1968 (Box 5)
    - "Industrial Design - Quo Vadis?" (Box 5)
      ms. drafts
    - "Islander's Design" (Box 5)
    - "The Real Jamaica"- County, Oct 1967 (Box 5)
    - "The Rivoli Murals" - brochure, undated (Box 5)
    - "Shaping a New World Through Design" - County, Jan 1967 (Box 5)
    - "This is Norwalk" - Fairfield County Magazine, Feb 1975 (Box 5)
    - "Tribute to Malcarney: Executive, Sportsman" (Box 5)
      (working title: "A Tribute to a Sportsman") ms. draft
    - "Tribute to Malcarney: Executive, Sportsman" (working title: "A Tribute to a Sportsman") (clipping), undated (Box 5)
    - "Tribute to Pert Prince" (Box 5)
    - "Why Not All-Electric Living-Units?" - Electrical Manufacturing, Oct 1940 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Memorabilia
  - Calendars, 1963; 1964 (Box 5)
  - Financial, 1950; 1964-1974 (Box 5)
  - Legal - wills (Box 5)
  - Military (Box 5)
  - Photographs (personal), 1928; 1930,; 1941,; undated (Box 5)
  - Printed material
    - Brochures, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Clippings
      - Articles about, 1928; 1952-1973,; undated (Box 5)
      - Articles about (peripheral mention), 1949; 1960-1974,; undated (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1961-1975; undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Design competitions (Box 5)
    - Exhibition catalogs and announcements (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Publicity (Box 5)
  - Real estate (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, oversize (Map-case 50)